welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
boom let's do some check-ins I'm excited
yeah I think that's it
welcome to the stoah I am Peter
Lindbergh the steward of the stoah and
this is a place for us to go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge of this moment and today
we've got my buddy in Gregg Henriques
and he's going to share his thoughts his
theories which I'm excited about and we
have Nick Lee mocker I think I
pronounced that wrong but you can you
can kind of correct me Nick he's going
to be the emcee of the question portion
and Nick is a good friend of the store
and he's a new buddy of mine and when I
go to Europe we're going to get
shit-faced together and the wisest way
possible stop being said I'm gonna hand
it over to you Nick you can introduce
yourself if you like introduce Gregg and
then and tell us how it's gonna go down
today yeah I'm Nick this is the first
time I'm hosting one of these stoah
sessions and I'm super excited to do
that yeah we have Greg Henriques so Greg
is an American psychologist he is a or
he's the professor for the combined
integrated doctoral program at James
Madison University in 2011 he published
a book called a new unified theory of
psychology and he's currently working on
a book called the unified framework a
meta psychology for the 21st century and
that's what we're gonna be discussing
today
so just logistic wise you guys can ask
your questions in the chat and I'll read
them out if you want me to meet them out
and yeah I'll warm Greg up with some my
own questions after he presents and
we'll take it from there so with that
being said Greg that's here great thanks
Nick first thanks Peter it's really good
to see you I really appreciate the
invitation you guys are doing
unbelievably important stuff you know
the nice edge here and I've enjoyed many
sessions of the stoah it's wonderful to
be here and share
my ideas Nick thanks for hosting
enjoying our contacts and it's a
wonderful opportunity to share some of
these ideas with you so I've been given
basically a format of say 15 20 minutes
of dialoguing about where I'm coming
from and so what I'm gonna share with
you today is a basic overview of the
Tree of Knowledge system and it's really
a tree of knowledge theory of scientific
knowledge in the 21st century so let me
talk to you a little bit about what it
is and then I'll share it with you I'll
share my screen I'll give you a little
bit of history so you can understand
where my background is so he mentioned
that I'm a psychologist in graduate
school I'm gonna give you a very
abbreviated version so we can get into
this but it is important to kind of know
where the frameworks coming from in
graduate school I'm a clinical
psychologist so I was learning the
various approaches to psychotherapy
learning cognitive behavioral humanistic
psychodynamic approaches and I was
really fortunate to have therapy
instructors and scholars who understood
that when done with integrity each of
the major modern approaches have an
enormous lot to offer and they can lead
to new insights and creativity in the
therapy room and have a lot of evidence
to support them and yet at the same time
there is essentially a problem of
psychotherapy that there are these
different paradigms but no consensus and
when you take the key insights from them
there is no backdrop of understanding
that allows you to weave those key
insights together so essentially you're
given the option as to whether or not
you're going to become a single school
practitioner so I'm gonna go straight
psychodynamic and a Freudian tradition
or cognitive or you become eclectic
eclectic means okay I'm just gonna
borrow and make it my own
and that doesn't that's not for a for
somebody and I'll just speak you know my
selves I really really emphasize
coherence that's what my from a
big-picture view so the Stephen Jay
Gould talked about hedgehogs and foxes
I'm a big-picture hedgehog guy I'm
looking for one big system often that's
where my intuition takes me so all of
these different systems with all the
different language is bugged me I
learned about what's called the
psychotherapy integration movement there
is an actual movement inside of
psychotherapy where people are
systematically exploring ways in which
the various paradigms might go together
so there's a society about 500 people
they have annual meetings and it's now a
very mainstream I actually took a
different approach than most of them in
thinking about this problem with
psychotherapy and I'll ask you to take a
second and think about medicine for a
second in the modern Western tradition
of medicine okay our modern Western
approaches to medicine are reasonably
well unified okay there are definitely
different approaches and there are
alternative medicines especially if we
go to the east and many individuals
question rightfully so in many regards
whether or not the institution of
medicine as its employed however if
you're a physician and you go and you
learn how to treat the body in a modern
Western way you learn about all the
organ systems you learn about the cells
you learn about the various approaches
you become a general practitioner you
could become a specialist but they are
unified relative to our basic
understanding of human biology okay what
I mean by that is the human biology
gives you a basic science it's grounded
in biology in general science of life
and that provides us a framework for
understanding natural selection genetics
and physiology starting with cells and
how they build organisms and then that
gives rise to a picture of the human
body as a nested complex set of
relations between cells organ systems
inter-process interrelated processes
between those and all of that ultimately
sets the stage for understanding how
they go wrong and then how they might be
fixed and modern medicine can be thought
of as many
since the pathophysiology analysis but
it's relatively unified so that actually
gives rise to an idea if you jump up a
level if you have all these different
psycho therapies wouldn't it make sense
that these therapies might be unified by
the science of human psychology so we're
in the mid 1990s here in terms of the
timeframe and basically I asked that
question I said to thyself hey
why wouldn't we have all the different
psychotherapies be grounded and attached
to a unified conception of human
psychology okay and in in addressing
that question I essentially discovered
something which I already knew but I
looked at it in a very new light and
that was I already knew it but I didn't
appreciate it and that is there is no
unified approach to psychology okay
there simply isn't but now I actually
had this question fundamentally in a
different way I learned like virtually
everybody if you go into you take a
psych 101 course right now they'll tell
you they'll say psychology is the
science of behavior and mental process
and the key word in that is science
psychology fundamentally is about
science is about asking empirical
questions engaged in observation
measurement construct validity analysis
of variables causal experimentation and
it is through that that we gain
understanding as opposed to say folk
psychology or save anthropology's
ethnographic approaches or any other
number of different contrasts we're
going to engage in behavioral science
methodology to understand what it is
that we're trying to understand but if
you flip that around you ask the
question what is it that we're actually
trying to understand and utilize the
descriptions behavior and mental process
and you look into the question about the
ways in which people define those terms
that's when you realize what I
discovered and what is actually very
well-known if you look for it is the
what I call the problem of psychology
and that is the terms behavior and
mental process these mean very very
different things to in to people
different paradigms to different bought
processes in other words there is no
consensus about what behavior and mental
processes actually refer to in the world
instead what you have is a wide variety
of different paradigms models and
language systems that construe the world
to define those terms in particular ways
and that's what you get when you get to
psychology which is you get a discipline
that is both pretty paradigmatic meaning
it's not unified and then multi
paradigmatic meaning that there are all
these mid-level perspectives that are
competing to provide a set of some
understandings for behavior and mental
processes that at some level commit to
the scientific methodology okay so the
commitment is to scientific epistemology
alright and the process by which you
measure and observe and try to delineate
cause-and-effect but the topic the what
I would call the ontological referent
what it is that we're actually talking
about in the world when we use the term
behavior and mental processes is not
defined at all instead what you have is
a multiplicity of different perspectives
okay and that friends is what's called
the problem of psychology and it
actually has been known basically ever
since psychology was a discipline so if
you go back to the original attempts to
define the term psychology as a science
that is we're gonna put it under the
modern scientific enterprise system
ology alright then you go to vote and
you go to a whole bunch of other people
I'm not going to get into the history
then you get behaviorism in America and
essentially what you have is a profound
set of disagreements about what it is to
define mind in relationship to say
matter do so scientifically and no one
and in 1920 one of the most perceptive
psychologists that ever lived
led guy Vygotsky called the field out on
this and said hey we have a problem he's
called it the crisis and every
theoretical and philosophical
psychologist ever since has acknowledged
that this is a crisis now the crisis got
boring and so ultimately the field gave
it up and decided that
no solution to the crisis but it is a
documented historical theoretical
philosophical reality that this field
has no consensus about what it actually
refers to and so I share that with folks
okay and I share the contrast with
biology now there people disagree of
course exactly what it is that
constitutes life but the fact of the
matter is is that virtually all believe
and agree that biology science of life
and they have a sense as to what life is
relative to not a bacterial cell is
alive an atom is not you might debate
about viruses but basically you can draw
a picture around what life is so it's a
fundamental problem of psychology okay
and that's what I stumbled into in the
mid 1990s and over a course of a year a
set of insights emerged that gave rise
to what I think I think that I stumbled
across a very very important problem and
ultimately I developed a system of the
Tree of Knowledge system that sets the
stage for solving that problem so
fundamentally I'm interested in solving
the problem of psychology which
basically means I'm interested in
developing a science of behavior and
mental processes coherently defined and
it turns out that that's a real hell of
a journey
okay so what is my solution and that's
what I'm here to share with you is that
ultimately I backed up into a solution
that I came to call the tree of
knowledge and the tree of knowledge
solution offers a new way to look at the
universe and our scientific knowledge of
it what do I mean by a new way
well first off let me say it also offers
an old way okay
one of the oldest perennial philosophies
is Aristotle's for you for example of
scale of nature okay where he argued
that there are minerals and there are
vegetables and there are animals and
there are people and indeed if you
recall the great chain of being then you
would add angels and God to that and if
you're familiar with somebody like Ken
Wilber you know his approach to the
great nest of being in this perennial
philosophy offers a particular kind of
perspective
this that is argues that you go from
matter to life to mine to soul the
spirit okay and I'm gonna share you with
you a picture that corresponds deeply to
ken Wilbur's version of reality and is
one that I think that there's an
enormous amount of correspondence with
there are some important differences
however I got there from a radically
different place when I got there through
in relationship is asking this question
what the heck is psychology
and fundamentally realizing that there
was no answer and I then stumbled into a
particular way of thinking so what is
the Tree of Knowledge Tree of Knowledge
argues fundamentally that the universe
is an unfolding wave of behavioral
complexity wave a behavior of complexity
starts with the Big Bang gives rise to a
material dimension where we talk about
the behavior of energy and matter on the
fields of space and time an over a
period of ten billion years we then see
the emergence in our particular lineage
of life life give rise to a radically
different dimension of behavioral
complexity in the language of the Tree
of Knowledge and I'll explain exactly
why but we all intuitively have a sense
that living entities behave erratically
differently than atoms or molecules on
their own over a period of several
billion years we see another jump in
complexity
according to acknowledge this is the
jump from life into what I call mind
mind is the third dimension of
behavioral complexity and finally there
is culture cultures the fourth dimension
of behavioral complexity I'm going to
now share my screen with you and I'm
going to show you a depiction of the
tree of knowledge so that I can then
walk you through these different
dimensions so you can understand what it
is that I am depicting in it so
here's the tree of knowledge it is a map
of the different dimensions of
behavioral complexity it's a map of
cosmic evolution if you're familiar with
the big history of big history you will
see very quickly that there are two axes
on the Tree of Knowledge one of which is
time another of which is complexity if
you're familiar with virtually any big
picture view of cosmic evolution you
will see those two dimensions and I
would argue that virtually every map of
science placed especially in the context
of an evolutionary view requires these
two dimensions but what's novel about
the Tree of Knowledge system is the idea
that there are nested dimensions of
behavioral complexity inside and above
the dimensions beneath starting with
matter the argument fundamentally is is
that what happens with matter is the
emergence of a dimension of complicated
behavior complicated behavior refers to
the idea that there are parts and they
interact they and they can create all
sorts of different kinds of novelty but
they are not complex adaptive systems
those of you familiar with complexity
series know in fact this is on several
listservs recently ed snowden recently
released a distinction between clear
distinction between different types of
complex systems there's a fundamental
difference between complicated systems
and dynamic complex adaptive systems the
Tree of Knowledge argues that
essentially what has emerged are full
three following matter three different
planes of complex adaptive behavior you
may if you're familiar with Star Trek if
some of you were Star Trek guys back in
the day you may remember Spock playing
multi-dimensional chess
well the tree of knowledge argues that
the universe can be thought of from a
human perspective in terms of where were
position as different dimensions or
boards of complex adaptive behavior one
of which is that follow matter one of
which is life one of which is mind one
of which is culture now why why are
these that
engines and this is one of the things
that the tree of knowledge answers
fundamentally it says what emerges with
life and then again with mind and then
again with culture our information
processing and communication systems
that give rise to new dynamic control
relations so take a cell what are the
defining characteristics of a cell it
stores information DNA transcribes
information RNA creates a complex
dynamic network and communicates with
other cells to create either colonies or
relations food description this
distribution and life fundamentally is
defined living behavioral processes are
defined as a function of those
information processing and communication
networks now fast-forward to 700 billion
years 700 million years ago and we get
right at the time of the Cambrian
explosion if you're familiar with the
evolution of animals you get an
explosion of complex bodies animals with
distributed nervous systems and a
centralized control center like a brain
that's a brain what is the brain the
brain is - an animal like the DNA RNA is
- a cell it's an information storage
processing computation system that
allows for the animal to move as a whole
entity and those animals also then
communicate with each other so once
again you get the emergence of a novel
complex adaptive plan of behavior as a
function of a novel information
processing and communications system and
this is what differentiates animal
behavioral processes erratically from
plants fast forward to about a hundred
thousand years ago and we see yet
another emergence and if we're following
the trail the trail says we should be
looking for the emergence of a
information processing system a novel
information processing system that
connects minds together that gives rise
to another feedback loop of complexity
that gives rise to yet another complex
adaptive playing field what is that that
is the emergence of language and
ultimately the emergence of
justification propositional language in
question-answer dynamics that build
belief value networks that coordinate
individuals in the form of culture which
then sets the stage for them to build
societies and we have seen over the last
50 thousand years the emergence of
culture but defined in relationship to
human language beliefs and values and
large-scale systems of justification
culture with a capital C so what do you
get here with the Tree of Knowledge you
get a map of the ontic reality in the
evolution cosmic evolution of behavioral
complexity but there are features to it
that are very unique you get a
distinction between the dimensions of
complexity and you get away then to
correspond those two distinctions
between different domains of science the
argument is that that the concept of
science Maps the ontic reality of
behavioral complexity and we can now
correspond our mapping our ontology zuv
science with the reality the theories of
science map with the reality and what
this suggests is that there's a way to
conceive of the different domains of
Sciences physical sciences biological
science social sciences as corresponding
to the different dimensions of complex
adaptive behavior if we do that what
emerges is a novel way to solve the
problem of psychology which I can get
into but the last piece I want to make
before I then open this up to questions
is for us to take a deep breath and
think seriously about this formulation
and apply it to ourselves if we take it
seriously what it means is we can see
ourselves as physical material entities
that have a weight have a mass of an
atomic structure we can then see
ourselves as physiological entities but
have cellular structures that are
communicating amongst themselves and
forming networks of organs and organ
system communication that gives rise to
a physiological whole we can see
ourselves as a neural mental entity
whereby our phenomenological conscious
experience somehow
pulls together our whole brain activity
gives us a perceptual experience and
that corresponds to our capacity also to
behave as whole entities and finally
there's narration there's the capacity
to self reflect and justify to ourselves
and to others what we are and to think
about the rules and programs of our
culture and decide what is acceptable
and what is not what that means is we
can think about ourselves across the for
quadratic layers of dimensions of
complexity and so I encourage us to see
whether or not that correspondence
allows us to sort the various behavioral
frequencies that are commensurate with
our perspective and the final piece what
I'll do is I'll try to bring us now
collectively together I'll think about
where we are in history and invite us to
consider whether or not this pattern
would continue is it the case then if it
is the case that there are different
information processing and communication
systems that get networked together and
if there are novel ways of forming
computation and these are the things the
ingredients that give rise to a complex
adaptive plane of behavior a new
perspective on our current situation
emerges I think many of us certainly any
people I talk to feel like we're on the
flux of something it's almost as if
we're in a time between worlds to use a
Steans frame or that we need to shift to
a game B equation it seems as though the
old blue church is not up to the task
it's as though things are happening so
quickly and so differently that our old
ways of being are being stripped and
there's a future of a force that is
almost unprecedented are causing change
that are novel different scary hopeful
how do we understand that from this
perspective well if we go to the 20th
century and we take the tree of
knowledge seriously what you see very
clearly is that you would simply ask the
question has there been the emergence of
novel systems of information processing
have they been networked together are
they interfacing both with human
intelligence and each other to create
artificial intelligence set and all of a
sudden you have a very clear picture
that before us is the emergence of a
meta cultural digital landscape and I
believe fundamentally this is the
problem of the fifth joint point and one
of the ways to characterize ourselves
and the time that we find ourselves in
is that we are actually in the process
of a transition through the dimension of
culture and justification which is
becoming networked together now with
artificial intelligence and internet
structures that are giving rise to what
Oliver Reiser of 1950 philosopher called
the world sensorial and so with that I
will pause and say here this is the map
ultimately this provides a framework for
understanding both what psychology is
and I argue now in my latest book really
this is a 21st century way to understand
the physical biological psychological
and social sciences so I will stop my
sharing the screen for them see Nick if
we if you want a riff off of that and
then we can pop into Q&A yeah I mean wow
so I remember the first time that Greg
walked me through this and just blew my
mind and now you just did it again
for a whole frickin audience so this is
so I mean obviously as we've got the
fifth joint point in going down that
rabbit hole of what that could be
that's that feels really alive to me but
before before we need to go there I
wanted to ask about something that that
Peter talks a lot about here on the
stoah is be in a right relationship
right or you talked about coherence in
the beginning of this talk and so I feel
like your theory provides an
intellectual way of understanding what
it means to be in right relationship
with reality or with nature and stuff
and then there's an embodied way of
course of doing that which is sort of
what we're making psychology and
practices could be getting at so do you
think that with you know meditation and
journaling or whatever it whatever it is
that
these methods provide that's the way of
getting us into personal harmony and
then if we do that at scale collectively
we get collective harmony and you know
we're able to create what-what Zach
Stein calls a unique self Symphony right
so is that our way to even manage to get
to that fifth joint point by doing these
sets of practices well okay so that's a
great set of questions let me see you
know sort of respond to them so I'll
just remind everybody that I'm a
clinical psychologist and have been
training clinical psychologists for you
know since 2003 here at the James
Madison University and that my concern
fundamentally is with well-being and
dignity and in doing and living with
integrity
so I'm fundamentally concerned with
wisdom and what I just shared with you
the scientific knowledge so I will offer
the idea that after what what I'm
sharing with you on this piece of the
equation here it's a sense making system
okay so that you can apply and put on
your tree of knowledge goggles to
understand and organize an enormous
amount of science the short story
basically is that the modernist
Enterprise the modernist scientific
enterprise set us up to have good
glasses frames of reference and ways of
understanding the material and
biological dimensions of complexity and
although we've made enormous progress on
the mental and social cycle as science
dimensions there remains huge chaos and
that chaos is contributing to our
inability to distill the information
that the psychological social sciences
have offered us and understand how to
utilize them for practical benefit now
why well ultimately that's what the tree
of knowledge says as well because the
modernist Enterprise failed to solve the
matter of mind relation and in
particular didn't understand social
justification versus scientific
justification so what we need is a sense
making system that puts psychology
effectively on top of biology and then
puts the social sciences effectively on
top of that if we have a coherence
making system for science writ large
well that's gonna help us and we
desperately need it as everybody talks
in the rebel wisdom crowd this crowd
were in a sense making crisis and so
what the tree of knowledge fundamentally
is about is about a set of cognitive
architectures that allows you to see now
that doesn't tell you how to live this
is a knowledge system not on wisdom
system the system behind me the tree
behind me it really represents really
what's called the unified framework now
embedded in the unified framework is a
whole set of structures that have on the
one hand are pure reason or scientific
reason maps for sense making which also
on the other hand have practical reason
in fact the right side of the tree if
you're looking at it here is the side of
practical reason the side of practical
reason brings in things like how do we
what is adaptive versus maladaptive how
do we foster healthy development what
fundamentally is human well-being and
how do we achieve human wellbeing in
relationship to ourselves relationship
to others and in relationship to the
natural environment and the emerging
digital environment those are
foundational questions and then finally
what are the principles and processes
that we enact to foster the right psycho
technologies okay then enable the
ecology of practices to foster growth
toward well-being I love what John for
Becky is doing in his in ecology
practice I love his dialogue owes us
that enables us to create inner
subjective context so we can be curious
with each other
accepting lobbying and also challenging
as we move towards goals in fact my
approach to mindfulness is called calm
Emma okay and that actually is an
acronym that calm is an acronym for
curiosity acceptance loving compassion
and motivated to our valued states of
being in other words it brings in the
kinds of psycho technologies that I
believe are conducive to healthy social
emotional processes and fundamentally
then to get to your question it starts
to set the stage for giving us guidance
for how we ought to live now it doesn't
tell you what to do that anyone that we
tell you recipe wise I think would be
naive and you should run away
but it gives you guideposts and
principles and reflections on the kinds
of values that we should use to
structure what it is that we might be
doing so that that was a good answer
yeah to say the least
so okay now now we're getting questions
coming in but but Peter had the first
question so I'll give it to Peter cool
thanks Nick
so my question is about psychotherapy
and I know that's sort of where you
started in your career and I geeked out
about all sorts of cyclic therapeutic
modalities like over hundreds acceptance
commitment therapy Gestalt focusing
transactional analysis whatever and I
burst in a lot of them and I learned
from a lot of them but they don't really
interact with each other quite well yeah
and so I think it's it's definitely
important to have these like meta
frameworks to kind of allow them to be
hosts in but I'm also curious about like
a kind of a seductive way in order to
get them to interact and so I was
thinking about having something like a
psychotherapeutic cafe here will be like
practitioners and they teach it and then
try to figure out how they can interact
with each other to see what emerges when
they interact so I'm just curious if you
have any thoughts on that and in that
approach well first off I'd be a
wonderful stoah approach you know the I
Wilson I will say there's now a long
history of exactly what you are
suggesting that's called the formal
academic home for people that have been
wrestling with this which has been
started since 1983 is the Society for
the exploration of psychotherapy
integration set okay and that's
literally professionals coming together
with notice the framing it's a Society
for the exploration of psychotherapy
integration so it is literally a
metaframe
that brings individuals together
precisely along the lines where you get
sophisticated dialogue and exchange from
various perspectives and then you
explore the processes by which you might
riff off of each other
blend them develop ways of
benefitting and exploring so so it's
been going on for a long time in fact I
was socialized to that I love that I
learned an enormous amount from it and
and really I've been really in addition
you know half my challenge was on this
what's the problem of psychology the
other half is what is psychotherapy and
how do you manage this dialectical
tension between unity on the one hand so
we actually have consensus is what we're
talking about and at the same time I'm a
complete anti-authoritarian I hate sorry
language wise okay so it's look it's
like you know III I do not want a script
and I do not want somebody tell me what
to do that's gonna crush my soul all
right so how do we actually get
coherence with without scripting and
dominating and asserting that my way is
better than yours allow individuals
their own exploration and their own
capacity to use John for babies term to
participate in the real dance of
themselves in relation good you cannot
pre script if you're actually going to
have a soul in relation so it's a very
very complicated relation I'd love to
have 25 you know in fact I do I host
individuals and have conversations like
so just let's last Monday we got a long
round of conversations about what is
mindfulness is the various elements
associated with it so I could go on and
on about that but I'll simply I'll pause
there see if there's any follow-up you
want to offer Peter but then maybe yeah
I do have lots of follows but maybe the
cookbook market and get you back on this
though and talk about yeah I'll simply
say you know since 2003 I ate for 12
years that I directed a combined
integrated doctoral training program I
taught an integrative psychotherapy uh
navigated this is my that's my
professional wheelhouse and life so
summarize thank you yeah awesome and as
a good follow-up that builds on that
Edward did you ask your question
this is something that I've been
discussing a lot recently in federal
circles is this tree of knowledge since
making system is helpful for perhaps
most practitioners trying to understand
and contextualize the various branches
of knowledge as a practicing
psychotherapist you see it would seem
counterproductive to just start talking
about these kinds of sense making
systems to clients who are dealing with
very personal problems so how do you
translate this down into treating a
patient where they are to make their
life happier and healthier without
feeding them a bunch of theory that
comes over their head might turn them
off
of course yes so I want to be very clear
my approach to you know psychotherapy is
not to start with the tree of knowledge
by any stretch my approach to
psychotherapy is to start with the
indigenous real relationship and
understand what the presenting problem
is the person in front of me and to
communicate both directly and indirectly
to the extent that's appropriate that I
in care and and deeply interested in who
they are and convey relational value and
establish an opportunity perhaps where
if if appropriate given the presenting
problem in my expertise I might be able
to help them okay
so the first thing that you want to do
it from a psychotherapeutic perspective
is you want to create a healing context
now I have a systematic approach by
which then I will assess psychosocial
functioning we didn't talk about it that
much but on the first the fifth branch
of the tree which is actually the first
one that's under psychotherapy the
psychotherapy side is
character adaptation systems theory okay
character adaptation systems theory then
translates the theory side of the tree
to an applied model of how people adapt
to the environment and it argues that
actually there are different systems of
mental adaptation I'll just list the
standard meaning words that we use
there's a habit system okay it's on a
base level you for where you form
procedural habits that are essentially
operate automatically outside
consciousness they're triggered by
stimuli they have contingency codes
essentially that you enact then you have
an experiential system this is what Carl
Rogers was deeply concerned about
organized by your core emotion and
perception but really sits in your heart
and tracks your sense of relational your
values effectively you also have a
relationship system your real attachment
system which is how you place yourself
in relationship to others intuitively in
terms of your working models relative to
your history like your attachment system
do you have a clear strong robust secure
attachment system or do you have a
disorganized and vulnerable attachment
system this this creates basically your
phenomenological architecture okay on
top of that you have your self conscious
justifying system all right so if I ask
somebody hey what brings you in today
what I am getting is their public
narrative that describes what it is that
they are that how they justify who they
are what's happened to them and what the
problem is okay and then between their
self conscious justifier and all what I
talked about from an intuitive
experience in relational position okay
what you have are all the defenses
because they're trying to regulate how
they actually feel how they think they
ought to feel and how they should feel
to meet so what I do is I then take an
opportunity I listen to their story I
convey relational value and I listen to
the various themes about apt ation
across their habits across their
emotions across their relationships
across their justifications to me into
themselves and how they describe their
interpersonal and developmental world
it's through that then that I enable an
opportunity for that both of us to
perhaps to the
a sense of awareness set the stage for
accepting what we can't change and then
identifying possible adapted pathways
that we could work on in therapy room
that would enhance their well-being
all right
wow there's a lot of good questions in
the chat but key are on did you ask your
question oh yeah don't know which or
let's go this was the top one the idea
of honestly taking the extreme
perspectives and full emergence onto the
other side to what extent are ideas like
a soul or a daemon merely analogies to
guide us on the bleeding edge of
emerging complexity because of course
for a sort of existed prior it suggests
there was something prior but of course
here emergence suggests things have been
created as we go so I'm just wondering
what your opinion as opposed to pers
yeah yeah so this is a great question
and I'll tell you my primary focus is
what I call on my metaphysical empirical
system and what I mean by that is I the
Tree of Knowledge what I just show you I
now characterize it as a descriptive
metaphysical system for our naturalistic
scientific knowledge and that's where my
focus is so so I am a naturalist in that
regard and my focus is trying to
understand the world through naturalism
and I and and I start with energy in the
physics concept of the word basically in
the emergence of matter and the
emergence of life the emergence of
nervous system mind and gotten
phenomenological consciousness and then
the emergence of self-awareness into
where we are here okay
when I use the word soul I'm actually
using it although I am appreciating and
embracing that term because I'm going to
make a lot of jumps to at least
metaphorical religious constructs but
actually I can use it also in
Aristotle's meaning of the term which is
actually the functional form of an
individual's life you know starting with
vegetative and then into animal and then
into living a human rational life okay
so my the functional form of my life
especially from my perspective is a good
word for
psyche or soul all right now I am a big
believer okay at multiple levels okay of
sort of our ultimate concern that
resides I offered a letter an open
letter to humanity where I frame what's
called the elephant son God
okay the elephant son God is my metaphor
for our ultimate good concern okay
whether it's Aristotle's notion of you
die a monic the ultimate you die a monic
endpoint or whether we're talking about
an Omega whether we're talking about ROI
Bashkirs meta reality or any number of
spiritual concepts that orient me toward
the ultimate good so I definitely it
would to say that yes I have a soul
that's the function of my life and a key
aspect of my soul is my ultimate concern
that's my fundamental concerns with
morality
I love thing money like Jordan
Peterson's analysis okay of the Bible
and the idea that well we could think
about heaven and hell in Supernatural
terms or we can think about it actually
on here and now terms okay so the Gulag
Archipelago is the story about hell on
earth right and and when you're in good
shape
and your well-being is being met and
that can be a story of heaven on earth
alright so so how do i cultivate my soul
toward my spirit and not become a demon
here on earth so that's that's the way I
would frame that and I am agnostic about
what's outside of the metaphysical
empirical edge that I am focused on and
you know God as I like to say god only
knows what's on the other side of that
and and embrace it if that's where your
faith takes awesome and then we have
Alex good oh did you ask your question
okay hey guys um I may have to break off
because I have to give up my computer
but I'll try and get it in um so I I
came across the old knowledge earlier
but this is really explained it
beautifully I thank you so much um the
my I reacted though when he was starting
to talk about the force you know the
next level of complexity at being based
on AI so I got some sort of background
in AI and I'm a bit of a skeptic for it
being taken too far so where I was going
is that the the the the first two levels
of complexity required some new physical
so the first level come yes first units
connect to cut some physical artifact in
first case to sell the second case the
brain okay next one didn't require a new
artifact but a reconfiguration of the
brain in more complex ways so my my
question is should we not be looking for
further complex we configurations of the
brain to take us to the next level as
opposed to some new physical silicon
based artifact right okay so I need to
clarify what I meant
so what I am saying is that there's a
digital landscape that is emerging okay
and I'm not saying that's all going to
be located in an artificial intelligence
all right I'm not saying that I don't
know I don't think people know what that
is I'm simply saying that the landscape
is being laid down for and the 21st
century is being set for it to see it
emerge okay and whether that emerges
based on a genuine full-fledged
artificial intelligence singularity okay
or whether it fundamentally emerges
through collective intelligence
experiences and a social technical
psychic web of connection all great
questions I don't think we have any idea
how artificial intelligence and human
intelligence and collective intelligence
are going to be fused and interface and
interact to create what
okay but to me that's um that's the
unprecedented of the second half of the
21st century I don't know okay but I do
know he what the tree of knowledge says
is that the ingredients are there and
something is happening okay to get to
your other point I'm I'm a be what's
called a behaviorist rather than a
physical base oh why I actually think
very much clearly what what science
fundamentally to me about behavior and
and I'm also very keen on semiotic
cybernetics information processing
complex adaptive system kinds of
behavior so you say yes it is true of
course we didn't build a whole new brain
but I would say actually the brain human
brain built a language acquisition
device information processing system
that is very much what I in fact call
mine three is actually a mind within a
mind
okay and functionally the linguistic
system and the language acquisition
device as you explicitly yoked together
our minds and an inner subjective
Highway essentially did then enable us
to create a meta animal consciousness
that allows our self consciousness to
connect with each other so you're right
if there's definitely not a physical
differentiation like the others but the
functional form difference of linguistic
language information processing as
opposed to neural phenomenological
processing is profound
[Music]
seems like you started with this desire
of it to get a unified approach or you
saw these disparate approaches and just
breaking that down into science wants to
observe objects as separate atomized
whatever and that sort of reject
reduction and reduce everything and then
build it back up does science have a
limitation that it's inherently not a
holistic approach or complex system
approach and that's you're trying to
build it up from
a scientific point of view so there's
all this layers and jargons that can
anyone keep up with all these words yes
so integral that's also very word dense
it's very work dance Amen so I'll just
put it this way science is not a
complete for me science is not a
complete system of justification it is
it's a description descriptive and
explanatory system ok but you need a lot
more than describing and explaining to
live and to make life meaningful
so I embrace the thing behind me is a
meta psychology and it can be thought of
as a scientific humanistic philosophy
where scientific is helping me describe
getting an objective for take on what it
is but also science doesn't do a great
job on telling me what my subjective
experience and why I have the aesthetics
that I do and it doesn't do a great job
of how we should define what our core
values are ok so if the big three then
that's why I ask about Wilbur often
talks about what we aspire to are the
good the true and the beautiful which I
which we used to aspire to and I hope in
the 21st century we get back to aspiring
ok the scientific approach dominated and
sort of an attempt at gaining an
objective analysis of the it and it left
behind our concerns about what's
beautiful and what's good a holistic
philosophy would embrace all three of
those and I'm interested in a scientific
humanistic philosophy what about a quick
ad about journalism is supposed to be
translating complex jargon to the masses
ok yeah well we certainly need I mean as
as everyone that knows me knows that I
am really interested in spreading you
know ideas to as many people as possible
I start stopped writing to my academic
audience and started writing to
Psychology Today and I've had many many
conversations my wife about ways in
which
you can turn this thing in and make it
accessible and I love journalistic
pathways that would do it as long as
it's done with integrity and and doesn't
you know in its desire to make it simple
then doesn't make it wrong awesome and
then maybe squeeze in keys question
which something maybe to do with the
fifth joint point as well hi Greg thank
you for explaining the tree of knowledge
in such detail and it was my first time
learning that so I really appreciate the
way that it was articulated my question
is you mentioned seeing ourselves as
narration as well as so and you've been
talking about the emergence of a meta
cultural digital landscape at the very
end I did want to ask you about what
that was called the Oliver Reiser world
sensorium but okay so um how do you see
internet structures it within the tree
of knowledge and more specifically
because you're coming from a behavior
perspective it seems like how do you see
psychology playing a role in dealing
with the maladaptive behaviors in the
emerging landscape in the internet
structures and I have to say I again
like super appreciate this top because
my background has been in psychology as
you can see I'm not putting up my face I
just would not like to be recorded but
there's an icon of the psychology symbol
upside down so mostly because it also
looks like the wait symbol I mean it is
the wave symbol for I love it yeah
thanks and then when it's upside down it
also looks like a mathematical symbol
for transverse allottee so I say all
that um only because I'm so interested
in this part of the the fifth way of
looking at things and love to hear your
perspective
okay so a lot let me break it up into at
least two parts of the question I heard
so one was about well what rare is the
internet on the tree of knowledge and
how do you understand that that's a
great question and it's important to
know what to have a real P for what the
tree of knowledge is so the key the tree
of knowledge is a map of the unfolding
wave of behavioral complexity okay and
and I should say it's a map of the
Natural Sciences so what is not on the
tree of knowledge are material cultural
tools which then grow into things like
the internet so it does not represent
everything it represents the dimensions
of behavioral complexity so putting a
building on the tree of knowledge
actually a building I would characterize
this material culture and I have
actually work on a chapter right now
that it clarifies the taxonomy of
actually how to apply the system okay so
it does take some practice
you raised a great question and we're a
wait a minute where exactly is this
digital internet thing the form of
behavior that is coalescing around it is
beginning to emerge and that's what the
digital landscape will be in
relationship to the concrete artifacts
that give right that are met material
culture that's actually they're a hybrid
between the material dimension and what
we humans build human tools at least so
there's that that's a that's a
conceptual taxonomy question great
question and actually something I've
wrestled with quite a bit and then the
finally the other issue is a totally
separate question about well what about
these maladaptive patterns okay and this
is one of the reasons that I was so keen
on trying to build a system is that this
is such an unbelievably complicated
question that it's that it's hard to
summarize hey I'm gonna summarize it in
the reef first and what I mean by that
is then whoa because we're gonna run out
of time here in 1980 1968 Martin Luther
King came to the American Psychological
Association and he opened with such a
profound and interesting thing that it
sticks with me when I read the the quote
he said psychologists you you have given
us a great word and that word is
maladjusted and he said and there are
some things to which we should always be
maladjusted all right
so if you're sitting in the audience in
your psychologist you're like oh yeah
maladjusted IO that's what I treat
maladaptive maladjustment and Martin
Luther King flips it around this ago
actually well what if the person is
miserable precisely because the society
is sick and they're maladjustment is a
sign of health relative to that sickness
if anybody watches you want to put it in
a family context anybody watches the
film ordinary people it's a great 1980
film won best picture and it shows a kid
who's bought his older brother died and
he's managing it and all of the
pathology that manifests in him anybody
that takes a family system to that
instantaneously can say that the
director Robert Redford you're saying
maybe the pathology is not in him but
maybe it's in what's around him okay so
my basic retort to you is the calm the
idea about what it is that we should be
adapting to how we should adapt how we
should adapt in a completely novel
environment and what we should decide to
be the problems or symptoms of the
problems turns out to be a profoundly
complicated set of questions that
pertain to philosophy values your
overall worldview and the scientific way
in which you define and that's why by
the way the problem of psychotherapy is
so unbelievably contentious and why
actually I had to simplify it and jumped
over to the problem of psychology
because that nested question of values
and how you actually then respond well
that's a dialogue for a lifetime or
that's an invitation back to this Noah
yeah that feels like a good place to end
this session thanks everybody for the
amazing questions and thank you Greg for
sharing all that knowledge I mean that
was incredible hey man I really
appreciate it it's great to be here and
you guys are doing or like I said you
guys doing a wonderful thing and by the
way you know I went to back embark
because he's a stoic you know cognitive
therapy fundamentally about stoicism and
you know in terms of an alignment with
my own values it's great to be here
excellent okay so in a moment there's
some closing thoughts but Greg my friend
thanks so much for coming on and they
said we'll love to have you back Nick
thanks for him seeing today everyone
thanks for the question John yeah
thanks ru Christmas guys done great
questions man really really give me some
stuff to chew on
yeah the thing is that there's so much
good question to choose from that's hard
to pick but then there's always like a
little tease for you to come back to
more for more slow actions so later
today we have 4 p.m. Eastern Time we
have Justin Murphy he's going to talk
about antisocial virtue or so that
should be fun RSVP on the website and
then after that at 6 p.m. Eastern Time
AJ Vaughn the shame educator is going to
do a shame breakthrough boot camp so
definitely check that out as well and
the stoah is based off a gift economy if
you're inspired to provide a gift just
go to the website the store CA you know
slash gift for more information alright
everyone thanks so much